Slavic and Germanic Languages and Literature, Department of; Records ua605.001
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Literature Records
1970/1984
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua605.001
3.0 cubic ft.
Contains departmental copies of German dissertations submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Biographical History
The New York State Normal College first introduced a course in the "methods of teaching...Greek, French or German" to students in the Classical Course in 1890. [Circular of the New York State Normal College, Albany, N.Y., for 1890 and 1891, p. 10]. In 1890 the renamed College was given the mission of training high school teachers in New York. As foreign languages were not taught in the Common Schools, no instruction in German was offered by the State Normal School. Students taking the Classical Course were required to have two years of German before attending the Normal College, presumably eliminating the need to teach the subject. [Ibid., p. 8] By 1904 a course in the "Literature of the German Language" had been added to the methods course. [Circular and Announcement of the Courses of Instruction, 1904, p. 29]. The revised mission of the College adopted by the Regents on December 14, 1905, effective September 1906, which changed the school into a four year liberal arts college for teachers, schooldesignation the school adopted a four year liberal arts curriculum. German was taught in the Department of until 1964 when the Department of Germanic and Slavic Languages and Literatures was created.[1] Courses included German language and literature.[2] Two programs were offered: A Teacher Education Program and a General Program both leading to the degree of Bachelor of Arts (B.A.), totaling twenty-seven hours.[3] The Department of Germanic and Slavic Languages and Literatures also offered instruction in Russian, Polish, and Chinese. The department endeavored "to expand the student's intellectual horizon to embrace a culture other than his own. The foreign language is at once part of that culture and the only medium through which an intimate sense of the total culture may be gained. Extra-curricular opportunities to practice the foreign language in an informal setting are offered by language clubs and language tables."[4] In 1967 the department expanded its program by offering a year long study abroad program at the University of Wurzburg in Germany. A Masters program was established in 1968 to provide sufficient depth to prepare the student for a career in teaching at the secondary level of for further graduate study.[7]
In 1970, the Department of Germanic Languages and Literatures was established.[5] The Department offered three programs leading to the B.A. Degree: A Teachers Education Program, a General Program, and an Honors Program which began in 1969.[6] The departments offerings were expanded in 1972 to include a Ph.D. in German.**8 The department offered a year abroad of instruction in Chinese at Nayand University in Singapore until a department of Chinese Studies was established in 197?.
The Department of Germanic Languages and Literatures merged with the Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures in 1996. German language instruction was eliminated on campus in 1997 with German language instruction now offered through an agreement with Union College. The Department of Slavic and Eurasian Studies was created in 1998.
Chairs of Department of Germanic and Slavic Languages and Literatures, 1964-1970
1964- George W. Kreye, Chairman
1966 Charles W. Coleman, Acting Chair
1967-1970 John Winkleman, Chairman
1970 John Spalek, Chairman
Department of Slavic Studies, 1970-1994
1970 or 1971(?)-1977 Alex M. Shane, Chairman
1977-1978 Rodney L. Patterson, Acting Chairman
1978-1980 Alex M. Shane, Chair
1980-1985 Ernest Scatton, Chair
1985-1988 Henryk Baran, Chair (?)
1988-1989 Robinson Harlow, Chair
989-1992 Henryk Baran, Chair
1992-1994 Robinson Harlow, Chair
Chairs of Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Literatures, 1994-1997
1994-1995 Harlow Robinson, Chair
1995-1997 Charles Rougle, Chair
Scope and Contents
Contains departmental copies of German dissertations submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has no series. Arranged chronologically and alphabetically thereunder.
UAlbany Academic Departments; State University of New York at Albany. Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Literature
- Vander Heide, Ralph Peter. Deutche Blatter fur ein europaisches Deutschland/Gegen ein deutsches Europa: A Cultural-Political Study, 1975 (Box 1 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 1)
- Broerman, Bruce M. The German Exile Novel After 1933, 1976 (Box 1 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 2)
- Hartzell, Richard E. Ulrichs Pathway to the "Other" State An Investigation of the central Problem in Musils Novel "Der Mann Ohne Eigenschaften", 1976 (Box 1 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 3)
- Steiner, Frank circa Manfred George: His Life and Works, 1977 (Box 1 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 4)
- Lennig, Hannelore W. Gunter Eich und Sprache: Untersuchung zu Wandel und Entwichlung des Sprachverstandnisses in seinem Werk., 1978 (Box 1 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 5)
- Nagy, George L. Ferenc Molnars Stucke Auf Der Deutschsprachigen Buhne, 1978 (Box 1 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 6)
- Kellenter, Sigrid. Das Sonell bei Rilke, 1978 (Box 1 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 7)
- Guenter, Walter P. Theodore Fontanes "Schach von Wurthenow" Wirklichkeil un Verklarung, 1980 (Box 1 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 8)
- Barber, Sigmund. The Amadis de Gaule of the compte de Tresan and W. circa S. Mylius: an analytical comparison of the sixteenth and eighteenth Amadis editions., 1981 (Box 1 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 9)
- Krolick, circa Margaret. The Esoteric Tradition in the Novels of Gustav Meyrink, 1983 (Box 1 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 10)
- Wehage, Franz-Joseph. Karl Otto Paetel: Leben und Werk eines Literaturkritikers, 1983 (Box 1 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 11)
- Geyer, Eberhard. Die Funktion der Elementargeister im Werk E. T. A. Hoffmans, 1985 (Box 2 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 1)
- Skwara, Erich Wolfgang. Hans Sahl: Leben und Werk, 1985 (Box 2 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 2)
- Steppich, Christoph J. Die Vorstellung vom gottlich inspirierten Dichter in der humanischen Dichtungstheorie un Renaissance-Philosophie Italiens und in der Dichtungspraxis des Deutschen Humanismus, 1986 (Box 2 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 3)
- Van Ness, Silke. Pennsylvania German in West Virginia: Language Variations and Language Attrition, 1988 (Box 2 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 4)
- Willard, Penelope. "Gerfuhl" und "Erkenntnis:" Ernst Tollers Revisions of His Dramas, 1988 (Box 2 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 5)
- Ebel, Christine K. Funktional-pragmatische und Struktural-syntagmatische Aspekte des heilsgeschtlichen Kontextes am Beispiel der Herzeloyden-Figur in Wolframs von Eschenbach Parzival, 1991 (Box 2 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 6)
- Macris, Ursula A. Otto Furth, das dramatische Werk der Wiener Jahre und Prosa im Exil, 1991 (Box 2 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 7)
- Kufner, Stephanie E. Nur einem menschen bracht dies amt zum politichen helden in Schillers Don Karlos, 1992 (Box 3 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 1)
- Straif-Taylor, Helga. Lothar Schreyers Das Expressionistiche Theater: Content, Background, and Translation, 1992 (Box 3 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 2)
- Weigel, Robert G. Zur Geistigen einheit von Hermann Brochs Werk: Massenpsychologie, Politologie, Romane, 1992 (Box 3 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 3)
- Posthofen, Renate S. George Saiko (1892-1962) Leben und Werk eines unbekannten grossen Autors, 1993 (Box 3 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 4)
- Wilson, Kelly E. Force and Love in the Works of Rainer Maria Rilke (Heroic Life Attitudes and the Acceptance of Defeat and Suffering as Complementary Parts), 1996 (Box 3 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 5)
- Giguere, Undine G. Frauen im Exil Untersuchung exilrelevanter Themenbereiche anhand der autobiographisch ausgewahlten Texte von funf Exilautorinnen (1933-45), 1997 (Box 3 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 6)
- Lorenz, Erich J. Ueberlegungen zu den unterschiedlichen kommunikationsbedingungen in ost- und westdeutchland, 1997 (Box 3 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 7)
- Loyola, Annette. The Role of the Woman in Wirnt Von Grafenbergs Wigalois, 1997 (Box 3 (Department of Slavic and Germanic Languages and Li), Folder 8)
- Department records, 1975-1999 (Box 4-5)
  Scope and Contents
  Faculty meetings and advisory council minutes (1975-1984); annual reports; MA exams and reading lists; program internal evaluations, self studies; program flyers and brochures; Gen Ed requirements for foreign language (1999)